<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jin</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Keyora</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Orcid</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Synergy With Magnesium</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2F61A27F4DF7822C18F789CC75314860</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T15:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Depression, Anxiety, Insomnia, Neurotransmitter synthesis, HPA axis</term>
					<term>Homocysteine, Stress resilience, Mood regulation, Sleep quality, Cognitive performance, Magnesium glycinate, 5-Hydroxytryptophan (5-HTP), Ashwagandha, L-Theanine, Vitamin B complex, Students</term>
					<term>Professionals</term>
					<term>Entrepreneurs</term>
					<term>Menopausal women Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress System Antagonism -Reducing Excitotoxicity</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 is a comprehensive nutritional formulation designed to address stress-related emotional, cognitive, and sleep disturbances through a multi-axis regulatory strategy.</p><p>The formulation integrates eight clinically supported bio-actives -including 5hydroxytryptophan (5-HTP), L-Theanine, magnesium glycinate, vitamin B complex, and Ashwagandha -each contributing distinct yet complementary neurobiological mechanisms.</p><p>Mechanistically, the formula enhances serotonergic and GABAergic transmission, supports melatonin synthesis, regulates the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) stress axis, and promotes neuroplasticity in prefrontal-limbic circuits.</p><p>Clinical evidence indicates its efficacy in alleviating depressive and anxiety symptoms, improving sleep quality, and sustaining cognitive flexibility in high-stress populations.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr">Lopresti et al., 2019 -8-week</ref> <p>RCT in high-stress but otherwise healthy adults improved perceived stress, sleep quality, reaction time, and heart rate variability; serum cortisol decreased significantly with no adverse events. c) Improved Sleep Quality in Insomnia Langade et al., 2019 -12-week RCT in older adults (&gt;65 years) showed shorter sleep latency, fewer awakenings, higher vitality scores, and improved PSQI scores over placebo; also reduced anxiety. d) Anxiety Symptom Relief in GAD Cooley et al., 2009 -RCT in mild-to-moderate GAD patients found 56.5% average reduction in HAM-A scores, with concurrent improvements in sleep and quality of life; superior to standard counseling. e) Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis Confirmation Pratte et al., 2014 -Review of five human trials confirmed consistent improvements in anxiety, sleep, and cortisol regulation, with no serious adverse events. Summary: High-Quality Clinical Evidence on Ashwagandha Functional Target Clinical Effect Reference Evidence Grade HPA Axis Regulation Reduces cortisol levels, Chandrasekhar A Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Functional Target Clinical Effect Reference Evidence Grade enhances stress resilience (2012) Anxiety Reduction Significant decrease in anxiety scores, alleviates mental tension Lopresti (2019) A Sleep Quality Improvement Shortens sleep onset latency, increases deep sleep proportion Langade (2019) A Multi-System Stress Relief Improves psychological, sleep, and heart rate variability indicators Lopresti (2019) A Consistent Evidence Across Reviews Systematic reviews confirm efficacy and safety Pratte (2014) A This table consolidates key findings from randomized controlled trials and systematic reviews, highlighting Ashwagandha's robust evidence base for modulating stress physiology, improving anxiety symptoms, enhancing sleep architecture, and delivering broad psychophysiological benefits with excellent safety. F. Dosage Form, Dose, and Safety Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 contains 200 mg/day standardized Ashwagandha root extract (≥10% Withanolides). This dosage and form have demonstrated efficacy and safety in multiple clinical trials lasting 8-12 weeks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Precursors</head><p>Tryptophan, the traditional substrate for 5-HT synthesis, crosses the blood-brain barrier via the LAT1 transporter, competing with other large neutral amino acids (e.g., leucine, phenylalanine, and valine). Even with sufficient dietary intake, this competition limits its CNS delivery.</p><p>5-HTP, as a hydroxylated intermediate, is a non-competitive transport substrate and enters the brain more efficiently, where it is rapidly converted to serotonin by aromatic Lamino acid decarboxylase (AADC).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. B6-Dependent Conversion -Ensuring 5-HT Synthesis Efficiency</head><p>The 5-HTP → 5-HT conversion requires pyridoxal-5′-phosphate (PLP), the active form of vitamin B6, as an AADC coenzyme.</p><p>Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Low B6 status can cause premature peripheral conversion of 5-HTP, reducing CNS serotonin availability.  Co-supplementation with B6 optimizes conversion efficiency and central bioavailability, forming a closed-loop mechanism within the formula. Serotonin modulates:  Limbic system (amygdala, hippocampus) -emotional reactivity  Raphe nuclei -HPA axis negative feedback  Hypothalamus -melatonin synthesis and sleep-wake rhythm Together, this builds an "emotion-stress-sleep" regulatory circuit. C. Core Role in Mood Disorders Low serotonin is a well-established neurochemical basis for depression, anxiety, obsessive-compulsive disorder, and stress-related disorders. 5-HTP supplementation can:  Suppress hyper-reactivity of the amygdala, reducing fear and hypervigilance  Enhance prefrontal cortex control, improving impulse regulation and emotional balance  Attenuate HPA axis overactivation, reducing physiological stress perception  Promote positive affect and social motivation D. Melatonin Synthesis Support -Restoring Circadian Rhythm and Sleep Architecture Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Serotonin is the sole substrate for pineal melatonin synthesis, which occurs at night through hydroxylation and methylation steps. 5-HTP supplementation:  Improves daytime mood stability  Enhances nighttime melatonin production, promoting sleep readiness, shortening sleep latency, and increasing deep sleep proportion  Particularly beneficial for sleep-onset insomnia and delayed sleep phase disorder, especially when comorbid with anxiety or depression  Functions as a bidirectional regulator -daytime mood stabilization and nighttime sleep repair E. Clinical Evidence a) Depression and Low Mood  Shaw et al., 2002 (Cochrane review) -Found significant improvements in mild-tomoderate depressive symptoms, with relatively fast onset and minimal side effects.  Poldinger et al., 1991-Showed efficacy comparable to SSRIs in mood improvement, but with better tolerability, making it suitable for individuals intolerant to medication or with functional mood disturbances. b) Anxiety Support  5-HTP increases CNS serotonin levels, reducing anxiety, tension, and irritability. -Review: B1 participates in energy metabolism and stabilizes brain energy status, with significant impact on mental symptoms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6) Vitamin B6 (Pyridoxine)</head><p>Vitamin B6 is an essential water-soluble vitamin that, once converted into its active formpyridoxal-5'-phosphate (PLP) -participates in over 100 biochemical reactions. It is a required coenzyme for the synthesis of several key neurotransmitters in the nervous system and is considered one of the rate-limiting factors in neurotransmitter metabolism.</p><p>B6 plays a central role in pathways regulating mood, stress adaptation, and sleep maintenance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. A Key Coenzyme in Neurotransmitter Synthesis</head><p>PLP serves as a cofactor in multiple decarboxylation and transamination reactions, directly contributing to the biosynthesis of:</p><p> 5-HTP → Serotonin (5-HT) via aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase (AADC)</p><p> Glutamate → γ-aminobutyric acid (GABA) via glutamate decarboxylase (GAD)</p><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Studies indicate that B6 supplementation can significantly raise GABA levels, easing anxiety and sleep initiation problems -particularly in "cognitive hyperarousal" insomnia. D. Balancing Monoamine Neurotransmitters to Support Positive Mood B6 is involved in the conversion of L-Dopa to dopamine (DA) and DA to norepinephrine (NE). Adequate intake helps maintain stable DA levels in the limbic system, supporting motivation and reducing anhedonia or low mood -especially relevant in "motivationdepletion" depression induced by chronic stress. Additionally, B6 contributes to one-carbon metabolism, indirectly maintaining Sadenosylmethionine (SAM) synthesis and neurotransmitter methylation capacity, positively influencing the stability of long-chain neurotransmitters and brain methylation status. E. Secondary Mechanism: Inhibiting the IDO Pathway and Tryptophan Diversion B6 participates in multiple transamination reactions in the kynurenine pathway, playing a key role in regulating tryptophan's metabolic direction. Adequate supplementation can inhibit tryptophan shunting toward neurotoxic metabolites such as quinolinic acid (QUIN), thereby indirectly supporting central serotonin synthesis and slowing the progression of inflammation-induced mood disorders. F. At-Risk Groups and Applicable Conditions Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Diets high in refined carbohydrates or plant-based patterns with low B6 intake  Individuals under chronic stress with elevated cortisol (accelerated PLP metabolism)  Users of oral contraceptives, antiepileptic drugs, or alcohol (which interfere with B6 activation and absorption)  Those with mood fluctuations, sleep disturbances, or high cognitive workload In Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1, B6 is included at a synergistic dosage (typically 1.3-2 mg/day or higher) to ensure stable operation of neurotransmitter synthesis pathways, forming the foundation for the formula's mood-cognition-sleep tri-axis modulation.  Supplementary Support -L-Theanine promotes GABA and dopamine release in the brain, increases alpha-wave activity, and induces a relaxed-yet-alert state. Vitamin B6 acts as a cofactor for the rate-limiting enzyme in GABA synthesis.</p><p> Applicable Population -Individuals with nervous tension, anxiety-prone personalities, daytime over-arousal, or nighttime racing thoughts.  Vitamin B6 is the essential coenzyme for aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase, which converts 5-HTP to 5-HT; deficiency leads to precursor accumulation with reduced functional output.</p><p> Vitamin D upregulates TPH2 expression, enhancing the CNS's capacity to synthesize 5-HT, while also mitigating risk for seasonal affective depression associated with low sunlight exposure.</p><p>Applicable Symptoms: Low mood, anhedonia, morning symptom worsening, blunted emotional reactivity.</p><p>2) Attenuating Chronic Stress Drive -Suppressing HPA Axis Overactivation and Cortisol-Related Symptoms Core Formula: Ashwagandha + Magnesium Glycinate  Chronic activation of the HPA axis underlies many depressive phenotypes, including early-morning awakening, irritability, weight loss, and decreased libido.</p><p> Ashwagandha is one of the most extensively studied botanical adaptogens.</p><p>Standardized extracts have been shown in multiple double-blind RCTs to reduce baseline cortisol by 22-30% and to alleviate anxiety, mood instability, and stressrelated symptoms.  Magnesium glycinate contributes from a neuro-electrical modulation angle: Mg²⁺ antagonizes NMDA receptors, reducing glutamate-induced excitotoxicity, while Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 glycine acts as an inhibitory neurotransmitter within the GABA pathway, strengthening stress-buffering capacity. Applicable Symptoms: Anxiety with depression, sleep initiation difficulty, irritability, HPA axis dysregulation. 3) Restoring Neurotransmitter Balance -Enhancing GABA and Dopamine Activity to Reduce Irritability and Fatigue Core Formula: L-Theanine + Magnesium Glycinate + Vitamin B6  Depressive states often feature diminished GABA and dopamine system activity, leading to tension, irritability, attentional deficits, and fatigue.  L-Theanine crosses the blood-brain barrier and significantly increases alpha-wave activity (as shown in EEG studies), while promoting the release of GABA, dopamine, and serotonin, creating a relaxed-yet-alert mental state.  Vitamin B6 is an essential cofactor for rate-limiting enzymes in GABA (GAD) and dopamine (DDC) synthesis, determining neurotransmitter functional activity.  Magnesium glycinate complements this effect by modulating inhibitory-excitatory balance, reinforcing overall neurotransmitter homeostasis. Applicable Symptoms: Nervous sensitivity, restlessness, inability to sustain attention, brain fog. Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 4) Supporting Neuroplasticity and Myelin Repair -Improving Cognitive Slowing and Emotional Recovery Core Formula: Ashwagandha + Vitamin B12 Metabolic Support  Depression is often associated with reduced neuroplasticity and inadequate BDNF expression, impairing the brain's capacity for emotional adaptation.  Ashwagandha has been shown to increase BDNF expression, promoting synaptic plasticity recovery and long-term memory consolidation, as well as improving learning-emotion adaptability.  Vitamin B12 is central to SAMe synthesis, enabling neurotransmitter methylation (e.g., 5-HT, DA) and myelin repair, preventing conduction delays that lead to suboptimal cognitive function.  Particularly beneficial for cognitive-decline-related depression or fatigue-dominant phenotypes. Applicable Symptoms: Slowed thinking, delayed responses, poor learning efficiency, cognitive impairment, mild brain fog. 5) Synchronizing Sleep-Mood Rhythms -Addressing Mood-Sensitive Insomnia and Circadian Disruption Core Formula: 5-HTP + Vitamin B6 + Ashwagandha + Vitamin D  High cognitive demand individuals, students, or those with anxiety-prone temperaments.  Vegetarians and elderly populations requiring neurotransmitter support. 7) Summary Table -Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 in Depression Intervention Intervention Pathway Core Nutrient Combination Applicable Depression Subtype  Anxiety is commonly accompanied by impaired GABA function, manifesting as lowered neural excitation thresholds, distractibility, and persistent mental agitation.</p><p> Magnesium glycinate suppresses NMDA receptor activity via Mg²⁺, mitigating glutamate-induced excitotoxicity, while glycine itself acts as an inhibitory neurotransmitter supporting GABA signaling.</p><p> L-Theanine, as demonstrated by EEG studies, increases alpha wave activitypromoting a relaxed yet alert neural state-while modulating central GABA and dopamine levels to relieve tension.</p><p> Vitamin B6 functions as a coenzyme for glutamate decarboxylase (GAD), essential for GABA synthesis; its deficiency may increase anxiety susceptibility.</p><p>Applicable Symptoms: Irritability, inability to relax, difficulty initiating sleep, mental restlessness, exaggerated psychological reactivity.</p><p>2) Buffering HPA Axis Hyperactivity Goal: Reduce Cortisol Peaks and Stress-Driven Anxiety Core Ingredients: Ashwagandha + Magnesium Glycinate  Individuals with chronic anxiety often exhibit HPA axis dysregulation, including elevated cortisol and disrupted circadian patterns, manifesting as morning palpitations, agitation, and hypervigilance.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><figDesc>High-carbohydrate diets (increased demand due to glycolytic load)  Chronic psychological stress and elevated adrenaline (increased metabolic clearance) High cognitive workload or prolonged attention demand  Frequent alcohol use or impaired gastrointestinal absorption (reducing B1 uptake and activation) F. Role and Synergy in the Formula In Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1, B1 acts as the "neuronal energy foundation," working with:  B6 for neurotransmitter synthesis  B12 for myelin integrity and methylation processes This synergy aims to:  Provide the energetic background needed for 5-HTP-driven neurotransmitter synthesis Prevent secondary mood fluctuations triggered by mental fatigue  Support stable neural tone in the cognitive-to-sleep transition period Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Benton, D., Donohoe, R. T., &amp; Sillance, B. (1995) -The influence of the vitamin B1 on mood -Neuropsychobiology, 32(2), 98-105. -RCT: Thiamine supplementation improved cognitive performance and subjective mood state.  Zhang, Z., et al. (2021) -The importance of thiamine (vitamin B1) in energy metabolism -Nutrients, 13(11), 1-17.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><figDesc>Merete, C., Falcon, L. M., &amp; Tucker, K. L. (2008) -Vitamin B6 is associated with depressive symptomatology in Massachusetts elders -Journal of the American College of Nutrition, 27(3), 421-427.-B6 deficiency is significantly associated with depressive states in older adults.  Dakshinamurti, K. (2005) -Vitamin B6 in metabolism and nervous system function -In SubcellularBiochemistry (Vol. 35,. Springer.-Mechanism details: B6 supports the synthesis of GABA, 5-HT, dopamine, and other neurotransmitters. 7) Vitamin B12 (Cobalamin) Vitamin B12 is a cobalt-containing water-soluble vitamin found primarily in animal-derived foods. Once activated in the body, it participates in myelin sheath synthesis, one-carbon Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 In Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1, B12 functions as a structural-support neuro-nutrient, forming a multi-dimensional support network with B1 (energy metabolism), B6 (neurotransmitter synthesis), and 5-HTP (neurotransmitter precursor) to sustain neurotransmitter pathways, myelin synthesis, and metabolic stability. Key synergies include:  Enhancing SAMe availability to stabilize dopamine and norepinephrine pathways  Mitigating Hcy-induced neuro-inflammatory activation to protect cerebrovascular function  Supporting long-term cognitive and emotional stability strategies for older adults or vegetarians  Reynolds, E. (2006) -Vitamin B12, folic acid, and the nervous system -The Lancet Neurology, 5(11), 949-960. -B12 deficiency impacts the central nervous system via myelin, homocysteine, and SAMe pathways.  O'Leary, F., &amp; Samman, S. (2010) -Vitamin B12 in health and disease -Nutrients, 2(3), 299-316. -Systematic review: Multiple relationships between B12, cognition, mood, myelin, not merely a vitamin for calcium-phosphorus metabolism in the traditional sense; it is a steroid hormone precursor with extensive biological regulatory functions. C. Strengthening GABA Pathway Inhibition to Relieve Neuronal Over-Excitation  Core Mechanism -Magnesium glycinate exerts dual actions: magnesium ions antagonize NMDA receptor overactivation, reducing glutamate-induced excitotoxicity, while glycine directly activates inhibitory neurons to enhance GABA efficacy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><figDesc>LiteratureSupport -Boyle et al., 2017 -Nobre et al., 2008. GABA / Glutamate / NMDA Regulation (Mg / Glycine / L-Theanine) Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Boyle, N. B., Lawton, C., &amp; Dye, L. (2017). The effects of magnesium supplementation on subjective anxiety and stress-a systematic review. Nutrients, 9(5), 429. -Systematic review on the effects of magnesium supplementation in anxiety and stress, supporting enhancement of the GABAergic pathway.  Unno, K., et al. (2013). Theanine intake improves the shortened sleep latency and nocturnal awakening induced by caffeine in rats and humans. Journal of Physiological Anthropology, 32(1). -Human and animal studies supporting L-theanine's role in GABA/DA modulation and alpha-wave enhancement.  Nobre, A. C., Rao, A., &amp; Owen, G. N. (2008). L-theanine, a natural constituent in tea, and its effect on mental state. Asia Pacific Journal of Clinical Nutrition, 17(S1), 167-168. -EEG study demonstrating L-theanine's alpha-wave enhancement and improvement of the relaxed-alert state. 2) Sleep Rhythm Mechanisms: Multi-Point Intervention via Precursor Supply, Neurotransmitter Modulation, and Rhythm Reconstruction A. Enhancing the Melatonin Pathway to Restore Sleep Onset and Circadian Synchrony  Core Mechanism -5-HTP serves as the direct precursor for melatonin, whichassisted by vitamin B6 and vitamin D -is converted via AANAT and HIOMT into melatonin. This pathway is particularly crucial for "emotion-related insomnia" and "delayed sleep phase-type insomnia." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Risk Groups -Vegetarians, older adults, and high mental workload populations frequently present with suboptimal B-vitamin metabolism or bioavailability.  Applicable Population -Individuals experiencing brain fog, slowed reaction time, or significant fatigue during prolonged concentration.  Literature Support -Reynolds, 2006 -Benton et al., 1995. C. Enhancing Neuroplasticity and Learning Pathway Adaptation  Core Mechanism -Ashwagandha elevates brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), promoting synaptic remodeling and memory-pathway reorganization, aiding cognitive recovery and long-term memory consolidation.  Synergistic Support -Vitamin B12 contributes to SAMe synthesis, boosting neurotransmitter methylation activity and enhancing synaptic responsiveness.  Applicable Population -Individuals with low learning efficiency, reduced cognitive flexibility, or stress-related learning impairments.  Literature Support -Lopresti et al., 2019 -O'Leary &amp; Samman, 2010.  Benton, D., Griffiths, R., &amp; Haller, J. (1995). Thiamine supplementation mood and cognitive functioning. Psychopharmacology, 117(3), 313-320. -Thiamine supplementation improves attentional stability and recovery from mental fatigue.  Reynolds, E. (2006). Vitamin B12, folic acid, and the nervous system. The Lancet Neurology, 5(11), 949-960. -Explores the effects of B12 deficiency on cognition, mood, and neural transmission. Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 III Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 and Depression Intervention Intervening through the "Neuro-Endocrine-Rhythm" tri-axis to restore the biological foundation of emotional stability Depressive states are not solely the result of a single neurotransmitter deficiency; rather, they represent a complex neuro-regulatory disorder involving multiple dimensions: insufficient serotonin synthesis, impaired excitatory-inhibitory balance in the CNS, chronic stress-driven endocrine activation, and compromised neuroplasticity. Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 targets five key pathological pathways in depression, delivering multi-nutrient, evidence-based support through its eight active components. 1) Targeting 5-HT Pathway Dysfunction -Bypassing the Tryptophan Bottleneck to Enhance Central Serotonin Activity Core Formula: 5-HTP + Vitamin B6 + Vitamin D  In depression, the tryptophan-to-serotonin conversion pathway is often compromised, especially under high-cortisol states where competitive transport across the blood-brain barrier limits tryptophan entry into the CNS.  5-HTP directly crosses the blood-brain barrier independent of competitive transport mechanisms, providing an immediate precursor for central serotonin synthesis. Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 -Nutritional Neuro-Psychiatric Intervention for Mood, Sleep, and Cognitive Resilience in Students, Professionals, Entrepreneurs, and Menopausal Women under Stress Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><figDesc>.,Turner, J., &amp; Del Mar, C. (2002). Tryptophan and 5-hydroxytryptophan for depression.Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews.-Cochrane systematic review -supports the efficacy of 5-HTP in improving mild to moderate depression.Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  L-Dopa → Dopamine → Norepinephrine via dopamine β-hydroxylase pathways B6 deficiency directly reduces the efficiency of these pathways, leading to decreased inhibitory neurotransmitters (GABA, 5-HT) and dysregulation of sympathetic monoamines, manifesting as anxiety, insomnia, irritability, and poor concentration.</p><p>B. An Essential Cofactor in the 5-HTP Conversion Pathway 5-HTP in the formula requires AADC to convert into serotonin, and this enzymatic activity is strongly dependent on adequate PLP levels. In B6 deficiency, 5-HTP is prone to premature peripheral conversion, lowering central serotonin elevation and potentially causing mild gastrointestinal discomfort (e.g., nausea). Sufficient B6 intake is thus the "foundational safeguard" for 5-HTP's efficacy. Combined supplementation of B6 and 5-HTP has been adopted in multiple clinical studies to accelerate and stabilize anti-anxiety and antidepressant effects.</p><p>C. Modulating the GABA Pathway for Anxiety Relief GABA is the primary inhibitory neurotransmitter in the CNS, and its synthesis requires PLP activation of GAD. When B6 is insufficient, GABA levels fall, resulting in:  Increased neuronal excitability and reduced α-wave activity  Longer sleep onset latency and more nighttime awakenings  Reduced emotional inhibition, manifesting as irritability, agitation, and hypervigilance Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 metabolism, neurotransmitter methylation, and homocysteine clearance -serving as a core factor for maintaining nervous system function, protecting cognitive performance, and suppressing neuro-inflammation.</p><p>Deficiency can lead to multi-level neuropsychiatric impairment, with markedly elevated risk among vegetarians, older adults, and individuals with impaired gastrointestinal function.</p><p>A. Supporting Myelin Sheath Synthesis and Axonal Conduction B12 functions as a coenzyme for methylmalonyl-CoA mutase (MCM) and methionine synthase (MTR), facilitating the generation of myelin components (e.g., phospholipids) from fatty acid metabolism, and supplying nucleotides for DNA and myelin synthesis.</p><p>Deficiency results in incomplete or degenerating myelin structures and slowed conduction velocity, manifesting clinically as limb numbness, paresthesia, memory decline, irritability, or depressive symptoms -often classified as "subclinical neuropathy."  B12 is the only nutrient capable of reversing early symptoms of subacute combined degeneration (SCD) and is used in functional nutrition interventions to preserve myelin integrity and stable nerve conduction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Supporting S-Adenosylmethionine (SAM) Synthesis and Neurotransmitter Methylation</head><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-  In the MTR-catalyzed reaction, B12 facilitates the remethylation of homocysteine (Hcy) to methionine (Met), which subsequently generates SAMe -a universal methyl donor in the nervous system. SAM supports:</p><p> Methylation activation of neurotransmitters such as norepinephrine (NE) and dopamine (DA)  Phospholipid synthesis and membrane stability  Epigenetic DNA regulation and maintenance of synaptic plasticity B12 deficiency reduces SAM levels, impairing stable neurotransmitter release and interregional brain communication, leading to cognitive inflexibility and diminished emotional regulation capacity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Reducing Homocysteine Accumulation to Alleviate Neuro-inflammation and Vascular</head><p>Toxicity B12 is one of the essential vitamin-dependent cofactors in the Hcy → Met pathway.</p><p>Elevated Hcy is neurotoxic and vasculotoxic, capable of activating NMDA receptors, triggering excitotoxicity, increasing blood-brain barrier permeability, and promoting inflammatory cytokines such as IL-6 and TNF-α.</p><p> Plasma Hcy ≥10 μmol/L is positively correlated with depression, Alzheimer's disease, and post-stroke cognitive decline.</p><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  B12 supplementation lowers Hcy levels, and its effect is enhanced when combined with folate and B6, making it suitable for individuals at risk of inflammation-related mood disorders or cognitive decline. D. At-Risk Populations and Clinical Manifestations B12 deficiency is most common in:</p><p> Vegetarians -B12 is exclusively found in animal-derived foods; long-term vegan diets carry a high deficiency risk  Older adults -Reduced gastric acid secretion limits B12 release and absorption, leading to "functional deficiency"  Long-term users of acid-suppressing drugs or metformin -Both interfere with intestinal B12 absorption  Individuals with malabsorption -e.g., atrophic gastritis, small intestine disorders, or post-surgical states Early deficiency symptoms are nonspecific, including memory decline, difficulty concentrating, mood fluctuations, mild depression, and slowed reaction time. Without correction, these may progress to peripheral neuropathy or cognitive impairment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Role in the Formula and Synergistic Value</head><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-  Its active form, vitamin D₃, directly modulates neurotransmitter metabolism, neuroinflammation, circadian rhythm, and neurodevelopment in multiple brain regions.</p><p>It plays a pivotal role in regulating serotonin (5-HT) synthesis, maintaining sleep architecture, and mediating mood-immune system interactions.</p><p>A. Regulating Tryptophan Hydroxylase 2 (TPH2) Expression to Enhance Central 5-HT Synthesis Central serotonin synthesis depends on TPH2 activity. VD₃ can activate the VDR → transcription factor pathway, upregulating TPH2 gene expression, increasing the rate of tryptophan-to-5-HT conversion, and improving serotonin availability in the brain.</p><p> In parallel, vitamin D downregulates peripheral TPH1 expression, reducing tryptophan's diversion into gut-immune system catabolic pathways (e.g., the kynurenine pathway), creating a "central priority" substrate allocation.</p><p>This bidirectional regulation has significant intervention potential for individuals with "low-serotonin" anxiety, depression, and circadian rhythm disorders.  Magnesium glycinate complements this effect by modulating ion channel activity to blunt sympathetic overactivation, thereby dampening physiologic hyperarousal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Supporting Melatonin Synthesis and Stabilizing Sleep Rhythms</head><p>Applicable Symptoms: Morning anxiety, persistent inner tension, mood lability, social anxiety, emotional collapse under chronic stress.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Improving Neurotransmitter Synthesis and Conversion</head><p>Goal: Support Balanced 5-HT and NE Activity Core Ingredients: 5-HTP + Vitamin B6 + Vitamin D  Symptoms such as chronic worry and anticipatory anxiety are often linked to central serotonin (5-HT) deficiency.</p><p> 5-HTP bypasses peripheral tryptophan competition, directly contributing to brain 5-HT synthesis.</p><p> Vitamin B6 is a coenzyme not only for 5-HTP → 5-HT but also for dopamine → norepinephrine conversion, playing a dual role in emotional regulation and sympathetic tone.</p><p> Vitamin D upregulates TPH2 expression, enhancing endogenous serotonin production and mitigating neuro-inflammation-driven anxiety. V Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 and Insomnia Intervention A non-pharmacological sleep restoration system targeting the tri-axis of neuro-transmitters-circadian rhythm-stress</p><p>Insomnia is no longer regarded as an isolated sleep disorder, but rather a complex state involving disruptions in neurotransmitter homeostasis, circadian rhythm dysregulation, elevated cortisol levels, sustained cognitive hyperarousal, and imbalanced neuroelectrical activity.</p><p>In the context of anxiety, depression, stress overload, and heightened neural excitability, symptoms such as sleep-onset difficulties, frequent nighttime awakenings, and earlymorning arousals often co-occur, forming a self-perpetuating loop of "sleep-emotioncognition axis dysregulation."</p><p>Keyora MoodFlow 8 in 1 addresses five biological pathways that underlie the onset and maintenance of insomnia through a multi-targeted approach.</p><p>It offers a scientifically formulated nutritional system that synergistically supports neurotransmitter activation, HPA axis modulation, GABA balance, melatonin precursor supplementation, and stabilization of neuro-electrical activity -ensuring efficacy, safety, and reliability.  In states of depression or high cortisol, tryptophan is shunted toward the kynurenine pathway via IDO, reducing 5-HTP availability.</p><p> 5-HTP crosses the blood-brain barrier without competing for tryptophan transport,</p><p>entering directly into the central synthesis route.</p><p> Vitamin B6 serves as a coenzyme for aromatic L-amino acid decarboxylase, a ratelimiting enzyme for 5-HTP → 5-HT conversion.</p><p> Vitamin D upregulates TPH2 and AANAT, enhancing both serotonin and melatonin synthesis at key enzymatic steps.</p><p>This forms the "5-HTP-B6-VD axis" for circadian sleep initiation.  EEG studies show insomniacs often exhibit altered alpha-delta wave ratios and hyperactive brainwave activity.</p><p> Magnesium glycinate acts as a dual-function NMDA antagonist and GABA activator:</p><p> Magnesium antagonizes NMDA receptors, reducing glutamate-induced excitotoxicity.</p><p> Glycine serves as an inhibitory neurotransmitter, supporting GABA-A receptor activation and neural calmness.</p><p> L-Theanine increases alpha-wave activity (relaxed wakefulness) and enhances GABA and serotonin co-release.</p><p>This non-sedative combination supports neuro-electrical balance and is ideal for hypersensitive neural types.</p><p>Applicable symptoms: pre-sleep mental overactivation, difficulty relaxing, heightened sensory reactivity (e.g., racing heart, muscle tension).</p><p>3) Regulating HPA Axis Activation Rhythms:</p><p>Reducing nighttime cortisol surges that cause early awakenings This constructs a regulatory loop for the "nighttime-cortisol-GABA axis." This reconstructs the "5-HT-melatonin-cortisol" circadian transition mechanism.</p><p>Applicable symptoms: circadian reversal, sleep-wake misalignment, post-travel or nightshift rhythm disruption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Alleviating Emotion-Driven Insomnia:</head><p>Enhancing mood stabilization and sleep restorative quality Core formulation: 5-HTP + B6 + Vitamin D + Ashwagandha  Emotional insomnia typically presents as "pre-sleep emotional intensification" and ruminative recall-worry cycles.</p><p> 5-HTP enhances emotional stability by increasing serotonin availability, reducing nighttime negative rumination.</p><p> Vitamin D modulates neuro-inflammation and immune rhythms, improving sleep quality under emotional burden.</p><p> Ashwagandha provides axis-wide support (mood-rhythm-stress), ideal for emotionrelated sleep disturbances.</p><p>This builds an integrated "emotion-neural-sleep" axis for long-term regulation. This pathway builds the biochemical foundation for emotional stabilization.  Magnesium glycinate inhibits excitotoxic glutamate activity and overactive neural firing, enhancing nighttime GABAergic tone.</p><p>Especially effective for stress-related insomnia.</p><p>Applicable symptoms: nervous tension, palpitations, easy arousal, heavy stress burden, fragmented sleep</p><p>3) Restoring Coupled Rhythm of Sleep and Emotion:</p><p>Breaking the "Insomnia-Depression" Cycle Core ingredients: 5-HTP + B6 + VD + Ashwagandha  Melatonin and serotonin secretion decline during menopause, while nocturnal cortisol rises-creating a "hyper-aroused at night" circadian disruption.</p><p> 5-HTP + B6 provides the necessary substrate for melatonin synthesis; vitamin D regulates expression of core circadian genes.</p><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996</p><p> Ashwagandha reduces nighttime stress reactivity and prevents premature earlymorning arousals.</p><p>Together, these form a regulatory triangle: 5-HT -Melatonin -Cortisol, enhancing circadian coherence. This dual-layer support -energy + neurotransmitters -stabilizes mood and restores daytime vitality. Functional benefits: Improves emotional stability, alleviates anxiety and depression, and provides biochemical support for melatonin synthesis.</p><p>2) GABA/Glutamate Neuro-electrical Balance Key ingredients: Magnesium Glycinate + L-Theanine + Vitamin B6</p><p> Glycine acts as an inhibitory neurotransmitter, while magnesium antagonizes NMDA receptors, mitigating glutamate-induced excitotoxicity.</p><p> L-Theanine promotes alpha wave activity and facilitates spontaneous release of GABA, dopamine, and serotonin.</p><p> Vitamin B6 is an essential cofactor for GAD and DDC, involved in the synthesis of GABA and dopamine.</p><p>Functional benefits: Relieves neuronal hyperactivity, stress-induced insomnia, and attention dysregulation. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
