<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jin</forename><surname>Xu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">|</forename><surname>Keyora</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Orcid</surname></persName>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">594839892714BB7AA401E6D00EFBEA0D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-11-18T15:26+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<label type="revision">a91ee48</label>
					<label type="parameters">startPage=-1, endPage=-1, consolidateCitations=0, consolidateHeader=1, consolidateFunders=0, includeRawAffiliations=false, includeRawCitations=true, includeRawCopyrights=false, generateTeiIds=false, generateTeiCoordinates=[], sentenceSegmentation=false, flavor=null</label>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Relieve Depression</term>
					<term>anxiety</term>
					<term>improve sleep quality</term>
					<term>and support cognitive performance under stress for students</term>
					<term>professionals</term>
					<term>entrepreneurs</term>
					<term>and menopausal women L-Theanine</term>
					<term>Depression</term>
					<term>Anxiety</term>
					<term>Insomnia</term>
					<term>Cognitive Function</term>
					<term>Stress</term>
					<term>HPA Axis</term>
					<term>Melatonin</term>
					<term>Neurotransmitters</term>
					<term>Students</term>
					<term>Professionals</term>
					<term>entrepreneurs</term>
					<term>Menopause. L-Theanine -Relieve depression</term>
					<term>anxiety</term>
					<term>improve sleep quality</term>
					<term>and support cognitive performance under stress for students</term>
					<term>professionals</term>
					<term>entrepreneurs</term>
					<term>and menopausal women</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>L-Theanine, an amino acid predominantly found in green tea, exhibits neuro-regulatory properties that may provide targeted benefits for individuals experiencing depression, anxiety, and insomnia, while also supporting cognitive performance under stress. This paper reviews its mechanisms across neurotransmitter modulation (serotonin, dopamine, and GABA enhancement), stress axis regulation (HPA axis balance), and sleep-wake cycle optimization via melatonin pathways. Evidence from clinical trials suggests that L-Theanine supplementation can improve mood stability, reduce physiological stress markers, and enhance attentional control, particularly in students, high-demand professionals, and menopausal women. The potential synergistic role of L-Theanine with other nutraceuticals is also discussed, providing a framework for integrative nutritional strategies in mood and cognitive health management.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p> GABA enhancement: Promotes GABA synthesis and synaptic release, shifting neural activity toward a more "relaxed" state.</p><p> Glutamate/NMDA modulation: Competitively inhibits NMDA receptor co-activation sites due to structural similarity, reducing glutamate-mediated excitotoxicity.</p><p> Neuro-inflammation reduction: Decreases stress-induced microglial activation, preventing prolonged "overheated" brain states.</p><p>L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women."</p><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-  Synergy: Works in strong synergy with magnesium glycinate to amplify GABAergic inhibition, reduce anxiety and tension, and improve sleep initiation.</p><p>2) Alpha-Wave Enhancement -Rapid Induction of a 'Calm but Alert' State EEG studies consistently show that L-Theanine significantly increases alpha-wave activity (8-12 Hz):</p><p> Alpha-wave enhancement: Reflects a state of relaxed wakefulness, slowing racing thoughts and emotional fluctuations.</p><p> Beta-wave suppression: Reduces high-frequency beta activity linked to anxiety and intrusive thinking, promoting a sense of calm.</p><p> Pre-sleep rhythm restoration: Alpha activity primes melatonin release and facilitates sleep onset.</p><p>Particularly beneficial for individuals with overactive thinking and difficulty "switching off" before bed. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 amylase and subjective tension scores, supporting its role in managing prolonged low-grade stress in real-world populations. II Triple Neurofunctional Mechanisms of L-Theanine in Anxiety Relief, Sleep Optimization, and Cognitive Support -Evidence from a Landmark Clinical Trial Hidese et al. (2019) published in Nutrients a rigorous randomized controlled trial (RCT) that provides one of the most comprehensive evaluations to date of L-Theanine's multiaxis benefits on anxiety reduction, sleep quality improvement, and cognitive performance enhancement. Parameter Study Details Study Design Double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized, parallel-group trial Participants 30 healthy adults (no psychiatric history, no prior use of sleep medications) Dosage 400 mg/day pure L-Theanine (administered in two divided doses) Duration 8 weeks (56 days) Assessment Tools -SCL-90-R (Symptom Checklist-90-Revised) -PSQI (Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index) -STAI (State-Trait Anxiety Inventory) -WCST (Wisconsin Card Sorting Test) L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Parameter Study Details -CPT (Continuous Performance Test) Primary Outcomes -Changes in state anxiety scores -Changes in sleep quality -Changes in attention and executive function Key Findings and Mechanistic Insights 1) Significant Reduction in Anxiety and Stress Symptoms  After 8 weeks, the L-Theanine group showed marked decreases in STAI-State and SCL-90-R total scores, with notable improvements in the anxiety, hostility, and obsessive-compulsive subscales.  This indicates stabilization of autonomic nervous system rhythms and improved emotional self-regulation. Mechanistic Basis:  Enhances GABAergic activity, suppressing sympathetic over-activation and reducing perceived anxiety.  Increases alpha-wave activity, inducing a "relaxed yet alert" mental state -ideal for individuals needing calm focus without sedation. 2) Significant Improvement in Sleep Quality L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  The L-Theanine group demonstrated a significant reduction in PSQI global scores, reflecting: -Shorter sleep latency -Fewer nocturnal awakenings -Higher subjective sleep quality Mechanistic Basis:  Promotes alpha-wave generation and strengthens GABA-mediated inhibitory signaling, facilitating parasympathetic dominance at bedtime.  Does not disrupt REM sleep architecture and avoids the residual sedation typical of pharmacological hypnotics.  Improvements were particularly evident in task-switching ability and sustained attention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanistic Basis:</head><p> Reduces cortisol-induced suppression of prefrontal cortex activity.</p><p> Enhances cognitive flexibility and attentional control within a physiologically relaxed state.</p><p>L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women."</p><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) Overall Significance</head><p>This trial stands as one of the most authoritative single-agent studies on L-Theanine, providing robust clinical evidence that:</p><p> 400 mg/day is safe, well-tolerated, and suitable for long-term supplementation.</p><p> Delivers multi-axis intervention across stress regulation × emotional stability × sleep optimization × cognitive performance.</p><p> Offers strong potential as a nutritional strategy for emotional wellness in healthy and sub-healthy populations. Anti-anxiety mechanisms of L-Theanine include:</p><p> Enhancing GABAergic transmission: Indirectly boosts inhibitory signaling in the brain, effectively reducing tension and restlessness.</p><p> Buffering glutamate excitotoxicity: Structurally similar to NMDA agonists, competes for receptor binding sites to lower excitatory input.</p><p> Inducing α brainwave activity: Promotes a "calm yet alert" state, rapidly quieting mental noise.</p><p> Lowering cortisol levels: Suppresses sympathetic-driven stress hormone surges.</p><p>Best suited for: Anxiety-prone individuals, sympathetic-dominant profiles, social anxiety, and test-related performance stress.  No major adverse reactions reported; long-term intake (e.g., 400 mg/day) shows excellent safety.</p><p> When combined with magnesium glycinate, 5-HTP, and Ashwagandha, marked synergistic effects are observed.  Suitable for mild-to-moderate anxiety or day-to-day anxiety management requiring immediate yet sustainable relief.</p><p>L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 2) Mechanistic Summary Table Mechanistic Pathway Primary Targets L-Theanine Mechanism of Action Neurotransmitter Modulation GABA / Glutamate / NMDA Enhances inhibitory signaling, buffers excitatory anxiety responses Autonomic Regulation HRV / Cortisol / α-Amylase Reduces sympathetic tone, increases parasympathetic activity, improves physiological calm Cognitive-Attentional Stability Alpha Waves / Working Memory Improves attention control, suppresses anxiety-driven distraction Safety &amp; Compliance Onset Time / Side Effects Rapid-acting, high safety profile, non-addictive, suitable for long-term use 3) Clinical Consensus -Professional Insights on L-Theanine in Anxiety Management A. "Rapid × Safe × Non-Pharmacologic" Anxiolytic Profile Confirmed  Hidese S, et al., 2019: 400 mg/day for 8 weeks in healthy adults significantly improved anxiety scores (SAS), sleep onset, and cognitive performance.  Lu K, et al., 2004: Single 200 mg dose induced alpha-wave enhancement within 30 minutes, with participants reporting greater subjective relaxation.  Unno K, et al., 2013: Daily L-Theanine supplementation during pharmacy student internships significantly reduced anxiety scores. B. Recognized as a GABAergic Alternative Supplement L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Unlike GABA supplements, L-Theanine crosses the blood-brain barrier and directly modulates neurotransmitter dynamics.  Clinically beneficial for exam anxiety, public speaking, and long-term anxiety states, with excellent tolerability. C. Nutritional Psychiatry Recommends Use in Subclinical &amp; Lifestyle-Related Anxiety  Can be paired with magnesium glycinate, 5-HTP, or adaptogens to form a non-drug calming synergy system.  Especially indicated for highly sensitive personalities, environmentally reactive individuals, pre-sleep anxiety, and restlessness. 4) Recommended Target Populations Anxiety Type Rationale for L-Theanine Use Performance/Exam Anxiety Rapid alpha-wave enhancement, boosts mental clarity, reduces nervous tension Chronic Hypervigilance Buffers sympathetic overdrive, alleviates physical anxiety symptoms Emotionally Sensitive / Easily Startled Increases GABA activity, stabilizes neural reactivity thresholds Daytime Anxiety with Bedtime Restlessness Eases "racing thoughts" before sleep, supports natural sleep onset  Hidese S, et al. Effects of L-theanine administration on stress-related symptoms and cognitive functions in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrients. 2019; 11(10): 2362.  Supports the shift from a "high-alert" state to a "restorative" rhythm, aiding deep sleep quality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Synergy with Melatonin to Promote Physiological Sleep Initiation</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><figDesc>-Triple-Pathway Mechanism of Action GABA Enhancement × Alpha-Wave Modulation × HPA Axis Buffering L-Theanine is one of the most extensively studied natural relaxation agents. Its core mood-and stress-regulating effects are mediated through three major neurophysiological mechanisms:  Enhances emotional stability by activating GABA-mediated neural inhibition.  Inducing alpha-wave activity to promote relaxed alertness  Downregulating HPA-axis activation to buffer chronic stress and cortisol elevation 1) GABA Pathway Activation × NMDA Excitotoxicity Modulation L-Theanine enhances inhibitory neurotransmission and mitigates glutamate-driven excitatory overload:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><figDesc>3) HPA Axis Buffering × Cortisol ReductionMultiple studies demonstrate that L-Theanine attenuates hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis hyper-activation under chronic stress:  Cortisol reduction: Significantly suppresses stress-induced salivary cortisol spikes.  Sympathetic downregulation: Improves HRV (heart rate variability), restoring parasympathetic dominance. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Cognitive resilience: Reduces cortisol-related suppression of prefrontal cortex function, preserving executive performance under stress. 4) Relevance for the "High Stress + Anxiety + Insomnia + Poor Focus" et al. Effects of L-theanine on attention and reaction time responses. Journal of Functional Foods. 2012;4(1):381-388. -L-Theanine increased GABAergic activity and reduced sympathetic arousal, thereby improving attention and reaction efficiency in anxious subjects.  Juneja LR, et al. L-theanine -A unique amino acid of green tea and its relaxation effect in humans. Trends in Food Science &amp; Technology. 1999;10(6-7):199-204. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 -Demonstrated that L-Theanine promotes the release of GABA and dopamine, producing a relaxation effect without sedative side effects. Alpha-Wave Enhancement -Inducing Relaxation Brainwaves, Improving Focus  Nobre AC, et al. L-theanine, a natural constituent in tea, and its effect on mental state. Asia Pacific Journal of Clinical Nutrition. 2008;17(S1):167-168. -EEG measurements showed significant alpha-wave enhancement within 10-30 minutes of L-Theanine ingestion, indicating relaxed mental state and improved cognitive efficiency.  Gomez-Ramirez M, et al. The deployment of intersensory selective attention: a high-density electrical mapping study of the effects of theanine. Clinical Neuropharmacology. 2007;30(1):25-38. -Alpha-wave enhancement was positively correlated with anxiety reduction and working memory performance, particularly under stress conditions. HPA Axis Buffering -Attenuating Chronic Stress, Lowering Cortisol  Kimura K, et al. L-Theanine reduces psychological and physiological stress responses. Biological Psychology. 2007;74(1):39-45. -L-Theanine ingestion significantly reduced salivary cortisol levels, indicating downregulation of HPA axis activity and mitigation of excessive sympathetic-adrenal responses.  Unno K, et al. Anti-stress effect of theanine on students during pharmacy practice: positive correlation among salivary α-amylase activity, trait anxiety and subjective stress. Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior. 2013;111:128-135. -During practical training, L-Theanine reduced stress-related activation, lowering salivary α-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>3)</head><figDesc>Enhancement of Cognitive and Executive Function In WCST and CPT performance, the L-Theanine group showed faster reaction times and fewer errors.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><figDesc>Hidese S, et al. Effects of L-theanine administration on stress-related symptoms and cognitive functions in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrients. 2019;11(10):2362. -Daily supplementation with 400 mg of L-Theanine for 8 weeks in healthy adults significantly reduced anxiety and sleep disturbance scores, while improving executive function and attention. The study highlights L-Theanine's dual role in enhancing cognitive performance under stress. III Clinical Consensus on L-Theanine's Triple Neuromodulatory Mechanisms in Anxiety, Sleep, and Cognitive Support In contemporary nutritional psychiatry and stress management, L-Theanine is widely recognized as one of the safest natural amino acids with multi-target synergistic effects. It L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 is particularly suitable for individuals with mild-to-moderate mood disturbances, stressinduced neural imbalance, and cognition overload. 1) Anxiety Modulation Pathway: Suppressing Hyperactivation &amp; Restoring Relaxation Rhythms The core neurophysiology of anxiety involves sympathetic overactivation and excess excitatory neurotransmitter activity (e.g., glutamate), accompanied by diminished GABA function, elevated cortisol, and autonomic imbalance.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><figDesc>Hidese S, et al. Effects of L-theanine administration on stress-related symptoms and cognitive functions in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrients. 2019; 11(10):2362. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 -Daily supplementation of 400 mg L-Theanine for 8 weeks in healthy adults significantly reduced anxiety and sleep disturbance scores, and improved executive function and attention. The study highlights L-Theanine's ability to enhance cognitive performance under stress.  Kimura K, et al. L-Theanine reduces psychological and physiological stress responses. Biological Psychology. 2007; 74(1):39-45. -A single 200 mg dose of L-Theanine rapidly lowered salivary cortisol and modulated heart rate variability (HRV), alleviating acute stress responses. This provides clear evidence for L-Theanine's immediate benefits in acute stress management. 2) Sleep Regulation Pathway: Relaxation Induction × Transition to Sleep × Sleep Quality Enhancement Insomnia is not merely a matter of "being unable to fall asleep"; it often involves persistent cortical hyperarousal, racing thoughts, elevated evening cortisol, and delayed parasympathetic activation. L-Theanine's sleep-promoting mechanisms include:  Pre-sleep α-wave enhancement: Creates a natural relaxation rhythm, providing the neural foundation for melatonin release and sleep initiation.  Augmented GABA-mediated calming effect: Restores the pre-sleep inhibitory "neural braking" function, reducing cognitive hyperactivity.  Extension of deep sleep phases: Improves EEG spectral stability, increasing the proportion of restorative sleep. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Non-sedative profile: Unlike benzodiazepines, L-Theanine does not disrupt the REM cycle or cause next-day drowsiness. Applicable for: Individuals with difficulty falling asleep, cognitive overload before bedtime, or those seeking non-pharmacological sleep support.  Yoto A, et al. Effects of L-theanine or caffeine intake on changes in blood pressure under physical and psychological stresses. Journal of Physiological Anthropology. 2012;31:28. -L-Theanine significantly attenuates stress-induced increases in blood pressure, demonstrating a "mental relaxation × autonomic balance" physiological synergy. Suitable for inclusion in intervention strategies for "stress-sensitive, high-reactivity individuals."  Lyon MR, et al. The effects of L-theanine (Suntheanine®) on objective sleep quality in boys with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder: A randomized controlled pilot study. Alternative Medicine Review. 2011;16(4):348-354. -Pediatric clinical findings indicate L-Theanine significantly extends deep sleep duration and reduces nocturnal awakenings, without sedative dependence.  Hidese S, et al. Effects of L-theanine administration on stress-related symptoms and cognitive functions in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrition. 2019;11(10):2362. -Daily 400 mg L-Theanine for 8 weeks in healthy adults significantly reduced anxiety and sleep disturbance scores, while improving executive function and attention. The study highlights L-Theanine's concurrent role in enhancing cognitive performance under stress. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 3) Cognitive Focus Support Pathway: Mitigating anxiety-related cognitive impairment × Enhancing executive function × Maintaining cognitive stability under stress Emotional instability and stress states often directly disrupt prefrontal cortex (PFC) function, leading to reduced attention span, lower information integration efficiency, and impaired working memory. L-Theanine's cognitive-support mechanisms include:  α-wave enhancement × β-wave suppression: Reduces high-frequency "noise" brain activity caused by anxiety, improving clarity of thought.  Maintaining PFC activation: Mitigates cortisol's inhibitory effects on prefrontal function. Improving working memory and reaction speed: Verified in multiple double-blind trials.  Enhancing "relaxed focus" in a wakeful state: Particularly suitable for maintaining stable output during high mental workload. Applicable for: Students, knowledge workers, individuals prone to fatigue during frequent task-switching, and those preparing for examinations.  White DJ, et al. Anti-stress, behavioural and magnetoencephalography effects of an L-theaninebased nutrient drink: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover trial. Nutritional Neuroscience. 2016;19(3):137-147. -Administration of a nutrient drink containing 200 mg L-Theanine significantly enhanced MEG α-L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 wave activity, reduced subjective anxiety scores, and improved task performance. EEG/MEG data confirmed its triple effect: "relaxed brainwave state × emotional regulation × focused behaviour."  Unno K, et al. L-theanine, a green tea amino acid, prevents stress-induced brain atrophy by modulating stress hormone levels. Nutrition. 2020;79-80:110960. -L-Theanine prevented stress-induced hippocampal atrophy, via corticosterone suppression, sympathetic activation buffering, and reduction of neuroinflammation, confirming its structural neuroprotective role against "chronic stress-related neural atrophy."  Giesbrecht T, et al. The combination of L-theanine and caffeine improves cognitive performance and increases subjective alertness. Nutritional Neuroscience. 2010;13(6):283-290. -Although primarily a synergy study, L-Theanine alone also improved reaction time and -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798in the Modulation of Depressive States GABA Pathway Enhancement × HPA Axis Buffering × Dopamine/5-HT Support × Anti-inflammatory Synergy 1) Mechanistic Pathways: Four-Pronged Modulation for Emotional Stability in Mild-to-Moderate Depression A. GABA Enhancement and Neurotransmitter Stabilization  Depressed individuals often present with reduced GABAergic activity and overactivation of excitatory pathways such as NMDA/glutamate.  L-Theanine enhances GABA system activity while buffering glutamatergic stimulation, restoring an inhibition -excitation balance.  Concurrently, it exerts positive modulatory effects on both dopamine (DA) and serotonin (5-HT) systems, improving mood positivity and motivational drive. B. HPA Axis Modulation and Chronic Stress Reduction L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Depression is frequently accompanied by chronic hyper-activation of the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis.  Clinical studies show L-Theanine significantly reduces salivary cortisol, α-amylase, and sympathetic tone, targeting the persistent stress state at its source.  This helps transition individuals from a "locked-in high-stress mode" to autonomic nervous system equilibrium. C. α-Wave Enhancement to Restore Cognition and Emotional Responsiveness  Depressive states are often characterized by low α-wave activity, impaired attentional control, and increased rumination.  L-Theanine induces α-wave elevation, promoting a "relaxed yet alert" EEG pattern, which facilitates cognitive recalibration and emotional resilience rebuilding. D. Anti-inflammatory Modulation and Neuroprotection  Depression is closely linked to neuro-inflammatory profiles, including elevated IL-6 and TNF-α and reduced BDNF levels.  L-Theanine has demonstrated anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects in animal and cellular models, attenuating the neuro-inflammatory subtype of depression. 2) Mechanistic Logic of Intervention L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798Consensus: Nutritional Psychiatry Perspective on L-Theanine A. Widely recognized for its non-pharmaceutical, multi-target, mood-stabilizing properties. Featured in multiple nutritional psychiatry studies and dietary intervention guidelines as an adjunct for mild-to-moderate depression and stress-related symptoms.  Particularly suitable for individuals intolerant to medication side effects or in subclinical states.  Offers excellent safety, long-term usability, and no risk of addiction, tolerance, or withdrawal.  Williams NT. The role of L-theanine in reducing stress and anxiety. Am J Lifestyle Med. 2016;10(6):439-447. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 -A systematic review of multiple randomized controlled trials (RCTs) and intervention studies concluded that L-Theanine has strong evidence for modulating mood fluctuations, alleviating psychological stress, and improving sleep quality. The author recommends its use as a supportive intervention for mild-to-moderate mood disorders. B. International researchers recommend viewing L-Theanine as a "multi-functional neuro-modulator"  L-Theanine demonstrates synergistic regulatory effects with melatonin, GABA, and serotonin (5-HT), making it well-suited for integrated use in comorbid patterns of mood imbalance × sleep disturbance.  Particularly applicable to modern populations experiencing stress-related depression combined with sleep disorders.  Peuhkuri K, et al. Dietary factors and fluctuating levels of melatonin. Food Nutr Res. 2012;56:17252. C. Clearly defined clinical target populations, with broad application -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798clinical findings confirm stable efficacy and superior safety  Multiple intervention trials demonstrate L-Theanine's synergistic improvement of mood, sleep, and stress parameters.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><figDesc>Unno K, et al. L-theanine supplementation for stress reduction: evidence from human studies. Adv Nutr Res. 2022;13(3):772-781. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 -Clearly indicates that L-Theanine significantly regulates autonomic nervous system activity, reduces stress hormone release, and is well-suited for stress-induced mood regulation. 4) Particularly suitable for the following depressive profiles  Motivational-deficit depression under high-stress conditions (e.g., students, exam candidates, overworked professionals)  Sleep-disruption depression (characterized by nighttime mental over-activity and post-awakening fatigue)  Atypical/mild emotional burnout (subclinical low mood requiring long-term modulation)  Hidese S, et al. Effects of L-theanine administration on stress-related symptoms and cognitive functions in healthy adults: a randomized controlled trial. Nutrients. 2019;11(10):2362. -Daily supplementation with 400 mg L-Theanine for 8 weeks -Significantly improved anxiety scores, sleep disturbances, executive function, and sustained attention -Authors emphasize its use for emotional support under stress and modulation of subclinical depressive states  Unno K, et al. Anti-stress effect of theanine on students during pharmacy practice. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2013;111:128-135. -In a high-pressure setting (clinical internship students), daily L-Theanine intake significantly reduced stress scores and salivary α-amylase -Findings indicate L-Theanine may prevent stress-induced emotional exhaustion L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  Dodd S, et al. The effect of L-theanine and caffeine as cognitive enhancers: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2015;30(4):223-232. -Although focused on cognitive enhancement, the review highlights L-Theanine's "relaxation × stabilization" profile when taken alone -Suitable for improving attention deficits and implicit negative thought loops often accompanying low mood V L-Theanine in Anxiety Management GABA Enhancement × Autonomic Nervous System Balance × Attention Stabilization × Rapid-Acting Profile 1) Mechanistic Pathways -Multi-Route Modulation of Anxiety Onset and Maintenance A. Enhancing GABAergic Inhibitory Signaling to Dampen Neural Overactivation  Anxiety is frequently associated with reduced GABA_A receptor activity and excessive glutamate pathway excitation, sustaining elevated neural tension.  L-Theanine increases GABA synthesis and receptor binding efficiency, reinforcing central inhibitory signals and reducing neural hyperarousal.  It also indirectly modulates NMDA receptor channels, helping to alleviate excitotoxicity and muscle tension. L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 B. Autonomic System Modulation &amp; Sympathetic-Parasympathetic Rebalancing  Anxiety often presents with sympathetic dominance (elevated heart rate, sweating, gastric discomfort).  L-Theanine boosts parasympathetic tone, promotes alpha brainwave activity, and induces a relaxed physiological state.  Multiple studies show it lowers HRV stress indices, salivary cortisol, and salivary αamylase, markers of physiological anxiety. C. Improving Attentional Stability &amp; Reducing Anxiety-Driven Cognitive Interference  Anxiety can trigger negative cognitive loops and future-oriented worry, disrupting attentional control.  By increasing alpha wave activity, L-Theanine supports focus, emotional clarity, and working memory performance.  Particularly useful for exam anxiety, work stress-induced anxiety, and chronic hypervigilance. D. Rapid Onset as a Safe, Non-Pharmacological Option  Unlike SSRIs or benzodiazepines, L-Theanine acts quickly without sedation, dependence, or tolerance issues.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>L</head><figDesc>-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 -Daily supplementation with 400 mg L-Theanine for 8 weeks significantly improved anxiety, sleep quality, and executive function performance.  Lu K, et al. The effect of L-theanine on alpha wave activity and attention. Biological Psychology. 2004; 67(1-2): 77-84. -A single 200 mg dose induced a measurable increase in alpha-wave activity within 30 minutes, producing a clear subjective relaxation effect.  Unno K, et al. Anti-stress effect of theanine on students during pharmacy practice. Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior. 2013; 111: 128-135. -In medical students under sustained high-stress conditions, L-Theanine intake significantly reduced salivary α-amylase and anxiety scores.  Williams NT. The role of L-theanine in reducing stress and anxiety. American Journal of Lifestyle Medicine. 2016; 10(6): 439-447. -Systematic review evidence supports L-Theanine's significant value in anxiety reduction, stress management, and sleep quality improvement. VI L-Theanine and Insomnia Intervention GABA Enhancement × Alpha-Wave Induction × Autonomic Rhythm Regulation × Synergy with Melatonin 1) Mechanistic Pathways: Supporting Natural Sleep Onset and Deep Sleep Restoration A. Enhancing GABA Activity to Reduce Pre-Sleep Neural Hyperarousal L-Theanine -Relieve depression, anxiety, improve sleep quality, and support cognitive performance under stress for students, professionals, entrepreneurs, and menopausal women." Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996 Individuals with insomnia often experience symptoms such as "racing thoughts" and "inability to relax the nervous system."  L-Theanine promotes central GABA synthesis and receptor activity, while suppressing glutamate-mediated excitatory signaling.  Produces a steady onset without the residual morning sedation associated with hypnotic medications, making it suitable for daily long-term use. B. Inducing Alpha-Wave Activity to Enter a "Relaxed Yet Awake" State  Alpha waves represent the "physically and mentally relaxed" pre-sleep state and are a key EEG marker before sleep onset.  Multiple studies have shown L-Theanine can increase alpha-wave activity, helping transition from anxious or tense states to natural sleep.  Improves "can't fall asleep" and "rumination-type" sleep-onset difficulties. C. Regulating the Autonomic Nervous System to Promote Parasympathetic Dominance  Excessive sympathetic activation before bedtime is a core pathological factor in chronic insomnia.  L-Theanine can lower sympathetic indices in HRV, reduce heart rate and blood pressure variability, and increase parasympathetic tone.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Author: Xu Jin &amp; Keyora | ORCID: 0009-0007-5798-1996  L-Theanine may indirectly enhance melatonin's effects by lowering cortisol and stress-related hormones.</p><p> Provides a "pre-sleep readiness phase" via neural relaxation prior to melatonintriggered sleep initiation, improving overall sleep efficiency.</p><p> Particularly beneficial for "light sleepers" and those with circadian rhythm disruptions.  L-Theanine-induced α wave activity benefits sustained attention, information processing, and emotional resilience.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Mechanistic</head><p> Particularly suitable for students prone to "emotional drain" and "attention  -Design: 400 mg/day L-Theanine × 8 weeks; healthy adult participants under daily life stress.</p><p>-Findings: Significant improvements in anxiety scores, sleep quality, sustained attention, and executive function.</p><p>-Conclusion: L-Theanine exerts positive regulatory effects on cognitive performance under stress conditions.</p><p>-Implication: Suggests potential application in student populations facing exam-related cognitive load. -Population: Japanese pharmacy students in high-pressure clinical training.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>-Intervention: Daily L-Theanine supplementation during internship.</p><p>-Findings: Significant reductions in subjective stress scores and salivary α-amylase levels.</p><p>-Conclusion: L-Theanine buffers "situational stress"-induced mental fatigue, supporting pre-exam state management. -Type: Systematic review of L-Theanine and cognitive performance.</p><p>-Findings: L-Theanine enhances reaction speed, attention, and working memory without sedative effects; synergistic enhancement observed when combined with caffeine.</p><p>-  Evidence supports improved performance under multi-task or stress conditions.</p><p>Applications: high study pressure, distractibility, pre-exam anxiety.  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
